<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true relation of a brave English strategem practised lately vpon a sea-towne in Galizia, (one of the Kingdomes in Spaine) and most valiantly and succesfully performed by one English ship alone of 30. tonne, with no more than 35. men in her. As also, with two other remarkeable accidents betweene the English and Spaniards, to the glory of our nation.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1626</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 20 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00296</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10419</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118018</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853227</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853227</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18596</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00296)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18596)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 833:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true relation of a brave English strategem practised lately vpon a sea-towne in Galizia, (one of the Kingdomes in Spaine) and most valiantly and succesfully performed by one English ship alone of 30. tonne, with no more than 35. men in her. As also, with two other remarkeable accidents betweene the English and Spaniards, to the glory of our nation.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Mercurius Britannicus,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1626.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Galicia (Spain: Region) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History, Naval --  Stuarts, 1603-1714 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18596:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18596:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TRVE RELATION OF A BRAVE ENGLISH STRATAGEM, PRACTISED lately vpon a Sea-Towne in <hi>Galizia,</hi> (one of the Kingdomes in <hi>Spaine</hi>) and moſt vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antly and ſuccesfully performed by one <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ship alone of 30. Tonne, with no more than 35. Men in her.</p>
            <p>AS ALSO, With two other remarkeable Accidents betweene the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Spaniards,</hi> to the glory of our Nation.</p>
            <p>Printed for <hi>Mercurius Britannicus.</hi> 1626.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:18596:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18596:2"/>
            <head>A true Relation of a braue <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſtratagem practiced lately vpon a Sea-towne in <hi>Galizia,</hi> (one of the Kingdomes in <hi>Spaine</hi>) and moſt valiantly and ſuccesfully performed by one <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ship alone, of <hi>30.</hi> Tonne, with no more than <hi>35.</hi> men in her.</head>
            <head type="sub">With two other Remarkable Accidents betweene <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Spaniards,</hi> to the glorie of our Nation.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou ſhall here (louing Countrymen) receiue a plaine, full, and perfect Relation, of a ſtratagem brauely at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted, reſolutely ſeconded with bold <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſpirits, and by them as fortunately Executed vpon our Enemies, the <hi>Spaniards:</hi> Who, albeit vpon what Kingdome ſoeuer they once ſet but footing, they write <hi>Plus vltra,</hi> deuouring it vp in conceipt, and feeding their greedy ambition that it is All their owne; yet this great golden Fagot of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion may haue many ſticks plucked out of it, if cunning fingers goe about to vndoe the Band: as by this Galizian Enterprize may appeare.</p>
            <p>A pregnant teſtimony hereby being giuen, that if
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:18596:3"/>
the great Warriours of the Sea would ioyne toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and Thunder all alongſt the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Coaſts, the <hi>Caſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lian</hi> Kingdomes might eaſily be ſhaken, when ſo poore a handfull of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> being ſpread before one of their Sea-townes, was the fore-runner of ſo terrible a ſtorme to all the Inhabitants.</p>
            <p>Such a braue muſtering of all the Gods of the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean in one conjoyned Armie, would quickly make the great <hi>Donnes</hi> to alter their proud and inſolent Poeſie, of <hi>Non ſufficit orbis</hi> (the world is too little to fill their belly, when the <hi>Eaſt-Indies</hi> lies vpon one of their Trenchers, and the <hi>Weſt</hi> vpon another; yea, and compell them to dwell quietly at home, in their owne hot barren Country of <hi>Spaine,</hi> contented with a dinner of a few Oliues, a handfull of Reiſins, and ſuch poore traſh; not intruding into other Kings Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories, (eſpecially theſe fruitfull ones of ours,) to eate vp our fat Beefes, Veales, Muttons, and Capons, (Victuals too good for ſuch inſatiable feeders,) when whole Countries (might they ſwallow downe their fill) are nothing to be devoured at one meale.</p>
            <p>Come forth therefore you Renowned <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and by the example of a few Country-men of yours, plough vp the furrowes of your Enemies Seas, and come home laden (as they haue done) with ſpoyles, honours, victorie, and rich purchaſed Prizes.</p>
            <p>Feare not to fight, albeit fiue Kings bring their men of Warre into the field, for you haue a <hi>Ioſua</hi> to ſtand vp in your defence, and to bid them battell.</p>
            <p>And when you goe to draw your Swords, or to diſcharge your Cannons againſt the Iron ribbes of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18596:3"/>
the Armadoes of this Potent and bloody Enemie, Pray vnto the Lord toward the way of the Citie which he hath choſen, and toward the houſe which in that place is built vp for his Name, and Hee in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen will heare your prayers and ſupplications, and judge your cauſe, and deliuer theſe wilde Boares, and Bulls of Tariffa into your Toyles.</p>
            <p>To arme you for Action, for your Countrie, for your Fames, for Wealth, and the credit of your Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whenſoeuer it pleaſeth God, that you put to Sea, may you be proſperous, and ſpeed no worſe than theſe haue done, whoſe ſtory I am now going to ſet downe.</p>
            <p>One Captaine <hi>Quaile</hi> borne in <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> deſiring to attempt ſomething for the honour of <hi>England,</hi> and benefit of himſelfe and followers, by the Licence and authority of thoſe in <hi>England</hi> who might giue him leaue, got a Barke of <hi>Plimouth,</hi> which by him and his friends was ſufficiently furniſhed with Men, Victuals, and Munition: the Barke being but 30. tunne, and the men in her, to the number of 34. or 35.</p>
            <p>This Captaine and the reſolute <hi>Gyng</hi> with him went merrily to Sea, and ſailed too and fro, without faſtening vpon any purchaſe, anſwerable to their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, or defraying ſuch a Charge, as they and their Ship had beene at. Their fortunes in <hi>England</hi> were not great, and if they ſhould returne home with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome exploits, their eſtates would be leſſe. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Captaine diſcouering his minde to his Lieutenant whoſe name was <hi>Froſt,</hi> they two (after conſultation betweene themſelues) perſwaded the reſt of their company to trye their vttermoſt aduentures,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18596:4"/>
rather than like Cowards to goe backe, who hearing the Captaines reſolution, were on fire to follow him, through all dangers, happen whatſoeuer could. And ſo they clapped hands vpon this deſperate bargaine, yet proteſting, and ſeriouſly vowing not to turne Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats, thereby to make booty either of their owne Country-men or friends to the State.</p>
            <p>Good hope thus, and a proſperous winde filling their Sayles, they houered along by the Coaſt of <hi>Gali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zia,</hi> which lyes vpon the head of <hi>Portugall,</hi> to the Northward. In paſſing by which, the Shippe being cleere, and the ſhores quiet, the Captaine comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them to caſt Anchor before a certaine Towne called <hi>Cris,</hi> which had a Plat-forme, or Fort with Ordnance to defend it; and this was done at Noone-day.</p>
            <p>Then, he being perfect in the French tongue, wrote a Letter in that Language to the Gouernour or Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of the Fort, importing thus much, That they were poore diſtreſſed French-men, driuen thither by ſome Turkiſh men of Warre, and flying to them (as to their friends) for ſuccour: pretending their grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt want to be Wood for firing, and freſh Water, to relieue them, of both which neceſſaries, they knew that place aboundantly ſtored, and for which they would giue any reaſonable content.</p>
            <p>Thus ryding at Anchor in ſight of the Towne, and their Cock boate being loſt in a ſtorme; they had no other deuice to conuey the Letter to the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Commander, than by ſending a Sayler vpon an emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Hogſhead, with an Oare in his hand to guide him
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:18596:4"/>
to Land, he being very skilfull both in the <hi>French,</hi> and ſwimming.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Spaniards</hi> ſeeing a man making to them in that ſtrange manner, thought verily they were men diſtreſt indeed, and thereupon Manning out of a Skiffe to meet and receiue him, they tooke him in.</p>
            <p>The Letter ſpake his buſineſſe to the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, who talking further in the <hi>French</hi> to the Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and being thereupon certainely aſſured of their diſtreſſe, determined to ſell to them ſuch commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties as they wanted, at as deere a rate as he could: and for that purpoſe commanded another Skiffe to bee Manned out with certaine <hi>Spaniards,</hi> who ſuſpecting nothing; haſtened to goe aboard the Pinnace, with their Captaine in company.</p>
            <p>In the meane time Captaine <hi>Quaile</hi> had ſhut his Port-holes cloſe, and hid his Ordnance: diſcouering not aboue fiue men vpon the Hatches, who ſeemed to carry ſickly faces, and weake bodyes, and were all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>armde. The <hi>Spaniards</hi> are joyfully embraced and welcomed: ſuch poore victuals as they had aboard were with arguments of much loue ſet before them: <hi>Holland</hi> Cheeſes were cut in the middle, and ſuch Wine and Beere offered them, as they were furniſhed with.</p>
            <p>This Entertainment carrying away all ſuſpition with it, Captaine <hi>Quaile</hi> inuited the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Captaine and the reſt of his company to his Cabbin. In paſſing to which, the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Commander eſpied a peece of Ordnance; at which ſtarting backe, and not halfe well pleaſed, demanding why it lay there, <hi>Quaile</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:18596:5"/>
it, and ſaid, that was all the protection they car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed about them, to defend them from dangers: and ſo with as much Cunning as hee could, hee drew by complement, and diſguiſed faire language, all the <hi>Spaniards</hi> into his Cabbin: whither with good words he welcommed them, and ſaluted them with Cannes of Wine, which whiles they were toſſing (albeit the <hi>Spaniard</hi> is the moſt temperate drinker in the world) and Captaine <hi>Quaile</hi> with his foote giuing a knocke for more; That ſigne of the foot was a watch-word to fetch vp all his Marriners; who crying <hi>St. George,</hi> appeared in their full number, euery man armde with a chargde Piſtoll, and ſhort Sword drawne in his hand.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Spaniards</hi> aſtoniſhed at this vnexpected ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall, ſeeing no remedy, yeelded themſelues, and ſo were all taken priſoners: an aſſurance being giuen them by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Captaine vpon the oath of a Souldier (his honour) and the faith of an <hi>Engliſh</hi>-man, which to an Enemy he ſcornes to breake, not a <hi>Spaniard</hi> there ſhould be in any danger for his life, ſo they would be quiet and ſilent, otherwiſe Death.</p>
            <p>Certaine Fiſhermen were all this while round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them at their labour, yet perceiued nothing.</p>
            <p>With all ſpeed therefore that poſſibly could bee vſed, Captaine <hi>Quaile</hi> and his Lieutenant making their Priſoners ſure, Manned out the two <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Skiffes with his <hi>Engliſh</hi> Muskatiers, euery one of them lying downe in the Skiffes flat on his belly, none (that might be miſtruſted, being ſeene) but ſuch onely as Rowed the two Skiffes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:18596:5"/>Then, with great Circumſpection (attended vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by a reſolution to meete Death face to face) they landed themſelues, and (actiue as fire) ſuddenly with little or no danger at all, ſurprized the Plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, and with the ſame dexteritie were Maſters of the Fort: for the act being quicke as lightning, ſo amazed the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> that it tooke from them all apprehenſion not onely of feare, but preuention, or acknowledgement of that danger which trod vpon their heeles. So that Captaine <hi>Quaile,</hi> what with his owne ſucceſſe and the others aſtoniſhment, in a ſhort time, and without reſiſtance, ſeized vpon the Ordnance of the Plat-forme, which turning and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging vpon the Towne, and his owne Barke like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe giuing fire to her Pieces on the other ſide, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ranne the people, to the number of Two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred perſons, beſides Women and Children. At the noiſe of theſe ſudden terrours, the Fiſhermen likewiſe, cutting their Nets, haſtened as faſt as they could to ſhore, hauing more care to ſaue themſelues than to catch any Fiſh; and ſo flying vp into the Countrey, the Towne was left naked, and letten to new Land-lords. Who meeting no <hi>Spaniards</hi> wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to be their Tenants, and the <hi>Engliſh</hi>-men them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues being loath to tarrie amongſt ſuch bad neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, they rifled both the Fort and the Towne, and had the Pillaging of both, for Eight houres to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. In which time, they hurried to their Ship any thing that was of value, and beſides the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of much riches, they brought away the Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:18596:6"/>
of the Fort, the Bell out of the Church, and the Challice: and ſo (without wrong to their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons) putting their <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Priſoners into their owne Skiffes, to ſhore they ſent them, with a warlike, tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphing Farwell from their owne Pieces, and are now with much honour arriued in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If this Example noble Country-men cannot giue you ſufficient Incouragement, doe but looke backe into the former Ages, and take a briefe ſuruay what Honourable attempts, exploits, vndertakings, and ſtratagems, haue in forraigne Countries beene en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprized and atchieued by the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> when braue <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Gaunt,</hi> Duke of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> &amp;c. beeing but a Subiect, without borrowing or charging of the Kings treaſures, out of his owne Purſe and Coffers, and aſſiſted by his Friends and ſuch voluntary Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, as craued dependance vpon his Fortunes, without Preſſe or compelling any man, beating vp his Drummes, leauied ſo ſufficient an Army, that with it hee Conquered all <hi>Spaine,</hi> remoued the V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurper, and reinſtated the expulſed <hi>Don Pedro,</hi> and after by Interchangeable Marriages, made himſelfe and ſucceſſiue Iſſue, compettitors and allies to the Crowne and Dignitie Imperiall.</p>
            <p>Of what Honours our Nation haue purchaſed from the <hi>French,</hi> euen their owne Chronicles, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the flatterie of ours, giue ample and ſufficient teſtimonie: Witneſſe the Battailes of <hi>Poytiers</hi> and <hi>Creſſie,</hi> fought by the Inuincible Souldier (for the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:18596:6"/>
great terrour which hee brought into <hi>France</hi>) called the <hi>Blacke Prince,</hi> who with Inimitable valour, Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage vndaunted, and expedition almoſt beyond hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine apprehenſion againſt infinite oddes, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing on his owne partie to incourage him, ſaue want of number and diſaduantage of place, yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, not onely deſrouted their mightie Armies, killing many and defeating all. But brought the King <hi>Dolphin,</hi> and all the Prince peeres of the land Priſoners, and preſented them at the feete of his Father.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Scotch</hi> King, taking the aduantage of the King of <hi>Englands</hi> then being in <hi>France,</hi> who lay at <hi>Calice,</hi> made Inrodes and Incurſions into this Land, whom the Queene <hi>Philip</hi> then deſtitute of all her Nobilitie and Gentry, as being then with the King her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band in <hi>France</hi>) met with an Army of Prieſts, Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmen, Artificers, and ſome few Gentlemen, gaue him Battaile, vanquiſht his Armie, tooke him Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, and added one thing more to the eternizing of her Husbands and Sonnes famous and renowned valours.</p>
            <p>I omit the great Battaile fought by <hi>Henry</hi> the Fift at <hi>Agincourt,</hi> with many others, and leaſt I be taxed of too great a digreſſion returne to the former diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe by me promiſed, and I make no queſtion by you expected.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Lisbone</hi> not long ſince,<note place="margin">The <hi>2.</hi> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of our Nation.</note> a young Marchant (who for diuers reſpects deſires to haue his name concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, being in the company of certaine <hi>Donnes,</hi> and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:18596:7"/>
falling in diſcourſe about the valour of ſeuerall Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, they ſo farre exceeded in the hyperbolies of their owne praiſe, that they bluſht not to affirme, that one <hi>Spaniard</hi> was able to beate two <hi>Engliſh</hi>-men out of the Field, which they in their braggadeſme inforced ſo farre, that though the reſt were ſilent, this young Gentleman not able to conceale a true Engliſh ſpirit, after ſome retort of language, there made a proteſtation, That if it pleaſed the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to giue him leaue, hee himſelfe would vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, (making choiſe of his Weapon) to fight ſingly againſt three of the proudeſt Champions they would produce againſt him; to cut off Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, the Chalenge was accepted, the Gouernour prepared the combitants, with the time and place appointed: a great confluence of people aſſembled: where one young Merchant, armed onely with his Sword and a Spaniſh Pike in the liſts appeared, who by the three aduerſaries was boldly and reſolutely charged: but God and his good Cauſe defended him ſo well, that the Combate continued not long, till one of them he had layd dead at his foote, and hauing receiued from them ſome few ſcratches, with the loſſe of a ſmall quantitie of blood, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out danger, hee ſo actiuely and reſolutely behaued himſelfe againſt the ſuruiuors, that they after di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers wounds from him receiued begin to quaile in their former courage, and fight more faintly and further off, which the Gouernour perceiuing, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the Combat to ceaſe, and withall to guard him
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:18596:7"/>
the Engliſh-man from the furie of the diſpleaſed multitude, who could haue found in their hearts to haue pluckt him in peeces, where calling him vp to him conueyed him ſafe to his houſe, and after much commendation of his valour, very nobly ſecured him to his Ship, wiſhing him for his owne ſafety to be ſeene no more aſhoare, whoſe counſell he follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and ſince with much Enuy from them, and great Honour to vs, he is arriued in his owne Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.</p>
            <p>I deſire to be tedious in nothing, but will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint you with another Exploit, no leſſe remarke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able then the former, performed in the beginning of this laſt Moneth <hi>Aprill,</hi> and thus it was:</p>
            <p>A worthy Gentleman one Captaine <hi>Warner,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The <hi>3.</hi> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</note> with two ſmall Pinaces was bound towards ſome part of the <hi>Weſt Indies,</hi> neither of them being of aboue 30. Tonne burthen: He being thus at Sea, was chaſed by a tall man of Warre a <hi>Dunkirker,</hi> who came to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them as if ſhee meant to ouer-runne them at once and bury their ruines in the bottome of the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean, which <hi>Warner</hi> perceiuing, pretended to make away with one of his Pinaces, as if hee purpoſed to ſaue a ſtake and leaue the other to the enemies furie and ſpoyles. The <hi>Dunkirker</hi> not able to faſten on both at once, tooke the aduantage of the firſt, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending when hee had ſeazed her to make like priſe of the other, hales her, boards her: his Saylers and Souldiers being all greedy of bootie neglect their
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:18596:8"/>
owne Ship, onely buſying themſelues in the rifling of the other, where I leaue them all buſie at worke; which <hi>Warner</hi> perceiuing, and not willing to ſlacke ſo good an opportunitie, takes the aduantage of the winde, ſuddenly caſteth about and ſeazeth vpon the <hi>Dunkirks</hi> Ship, whoſe men were moſt of them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board his other Pinace; boards her, takes her, mans her, and now being armed with her ſtrength Commands both his other Pinace, and all the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies aboard her, by which Stratagem, hee not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ranſomed his owne, but ſubdued his Enemies, made prize both of Ship and goods, and tooke all the men Priſoners. A noble incouragement to all the braue Captaynes and Commanders of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to ſtriue to Imitate him in his reſolution and valour.</p>
            <p>And thus worthy Country-men you ſee that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the proud braues of the publike Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my their ſcandals and calumnies, with all the aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of diſgrace that their malice can deuiſe, to caſt vpon our Kingdome and Countrey, maugre their Inuaſions threatned on Land, or their nauall try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs boaſted at Sea; how the great Creator of all things, in whoſe ſight pride, vaine-glory, and ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion are abominable, can when hee pleaſe by the hand of the youngman <hi>Dauid,</hi> ſtoope the ſtiffe-neck of the ſtrongeſt <hi>Goliah.</hi> And noble Country-men may theſe few Incouragements put into you the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Courage of your anceſtours, whoſe memories through all Seas, Nations, and Languages, haue
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:18596:8"/>
beene and euer ſhall bee Sacred to all poſterities. Now is the time of acting, and to ſhew your ſelues as you haue beene euer, Held and eſteemed braue in attempting, and bold in performing, and ſo without queſtion your expeditions ſhall bee ſucceſſefull, as the fame of your vertues Immortall.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
